你厨房里最便宜的东西可能是盐
You might think the cheapest thing in your kitchen is salt
一袋盐几块钱
A bag of salt costs just a few yuan
便宜到你买它的时候几乎不会思考
It is so cheap you barely think about buying it
但你有没有想过
But have you ever wondered
古代很多帝国最稳定的钱袋子
For many ancient empires the most reliable money maker
恰恰就是盐
Was exactly salt
不是黄金
Not gold
不是土地
Not land
不是丝绸
Not silk
而是你每天炒菜时
But those tiny white grains
随手撒进去的那一点白色颗粒
You toss into your cooking every day
更反常识的是
What is even more counterintuitive
盐之所以能赚钱不是因为它贵
Salt made money not because it was expensive
恰恰是因为它太普通
But precisely because it was so ordinary
普通到每个人都需要
Ordinary enough that everyone needed it
普通到每一天都要用
Ordinary enough that everyone used it daily
普通到你离不开它
Ordinary enough that you could not live without it
却很少会为了它讨价还价
But rarely bothered to bargain over it
这就是盐最可怕的地方
This is what makes salt so powerful
它不是调味品
It is not just a seasoning
它是古代政府手里
It was the ancient government
最完美的一台印钞机
The most perfect money printing machine
今天这条视频我们就用一袋盐
In this video we will use a bag of salt
讲透三个问题
To explain three things
为什么最不起眼的东西
Why the most overlooked things
反而最容易被定价
Are the easiest to price
为什么古代国家喜欢控制盐
Why ancient states loved controlling salt
以及在 AI 时代谁掌握了新的盐
And in the AI age whoever controls the new salt
谁就掌握了普通人的生活入口
Controls the gateway to ordinary people
先别急着想帝国
Do not rush to think about empires
你先想自己的厨房
Think about your own kitchen first
如果今天猪肉涨价你可以少吃肉
If pork prices go up you can eat less meat
如果奶茶涨价你可以不喝
If bubble tea gets expensive you can skip it
如果手机涨价你可以晚一年换
If phones get pricier you can wait a year to upgrade
但盐呢
But what about salt
你不会因为盐涨了几毛钱
You would not stop eating salt
就从此不吃盐
Just because it went up a few cents
这就是经济学里一个很重要的概念
This is an important concept in economics
需求价格弹性
Price elasticity of demand
翻成人话就是
In plain English it means
东西涨价以后你还买不买
When something gets more expensive do you still buy it
奶茶涨价你可以不买
If bubble tea goes up you can stop buying it
电影票涨价你可以不看
If movie tickets cost more you can skip the movies
但盐这种东西涨一点你还是要买
But with something like salt even if it goes up a bit you still buy it
因为它不是享受型消费
Because it is not a luxury
它是生存型消费
It is a necessity
你可能不懂经济学公式
You might not know economic formulas
但你每天买菜的时候
But every time you go grocery shopping
已经在用这个公式了
You are already using this formula
越是可有可无的东西消费者越敏感
The more dispensable something is the more sensitive consumers are
越是离不开的东西消费者越没得选
The more essential something is the less choice consumers have
这就是盐的第一层秘密
This is the first secret of salt
它小到没人重视
It is so small nobody pays attention
但它刚需到人人都要
But so essential everyone needs it
你想象一下
Imagine this
如果一个古代政府想收税
If an ancient government wanted to collect taxes
它可以挨家挨户去查田地
It could go door to door checking farmland
也可以盯着商人一笔一笔做账
Or watch every single merchant transaction
但这些都很难
But all of that is really hard
农民会瞒产量
Farmers would hide their yields
商人会藏利润
Merchants would hide their profits
地方官会层层截留
Local officials would skim at every level
可盐不一样
But salt is different
盐的生产地点相对集中
Salt production sites are relatively concentrated
盐井 盐湖 盐场 都不是你家后院随便能变出来的
Salt wells salt lakes salt pans you cannot just make them in your backyard
只要国家控制了产地 运输和销售
As long as the state controls production transport and sales
它就不用天天追着每个人收税
It does not need to chase everyone down for taxes
它只要在你买盐的时候
It just needs to collect when you buy salt
顺手收走一小部分
And take a small cut along the way
你不知不觉就交了钱
You pay without even realizing it
这比直接收税温柔得多
This is much gentler than direct taxation
也隐蔽得多
And much more hidden too
你以为你在买调味品
You think you are buying seasoning
其实你在给国家财政充值
Actually you are funding the national treasury
最好的税不是让你痛到反抗
The best tax is not one that hurts enough to make you rebel
而是让你习惯到忘记
But one you get so used to that you forget about it
盐为什么能撑起帝国
Why could salt sustain an empire
因为它踩中了商业里最硬的规律
Because it hit the hardest rule in business
高频 刚需 低替代
High frequency essential low substitutability
这三个词放在今天
These three words today
就是所有平台都想要的梦中情人
Are the dream of every platform
你每天打开微信
You open WeChat every day
每天刷短视频
You scroll short videos every day
每天点外卖
You order takeout every day
每天用搜索和 AI
You use search and AI every day
逻辑都一样
The logic is the same
只要一件东西变成你的日常入口
Once something becomes your daily gateway
它就不再只是一个产品
It is no longer just a product
它会变成一条收费通道
It becomes a toll channel
盐在古代是嘴巴的入口
Salt in ancient times was the gateway to the mouth
平台在今天是注意力的入口
Platforms today are the gateway to attention
AI 在明天可能是知识和决策的入口
AI tomorrow could be the gateway to knowledge and decisions
你看懂盐
Understand salt
就看懂了所有入口生意的本质
And you understand the essence of all gateway businesses
把镜头拉回两千多年前
Pull the camera back over two thousand years
汉武帝时期汉朝很强
During the Han Dynasty Emperor Wu the Han was very powerful
强到什么程度
How powerful
北边打匈奴
Fighting the Xiongnu in the north
西边通西域
Opening the Western Regions in the west
修路 养马 打仗 赏赐 管理边疆
Building roads raising horses fighting wars rewarding officials managing frontiers
这些都要钱
All of that cost money
而且不是小钱
And not just a little
帝国越扩张财政压力越大
The more the empire expanded the greater the financial pressure
你可以把它想象成一家高速扩张的公司
You can think of it as a fast growing company
办公室越开越多
Opening more and more offices
员工越招越多
Hiring more and more employees
市场越打越大
Expanding into more and more markets
看起来很风光
It looks impressive
但现金流天天在流血
But cash flow is bleeding every day
这时候老板会盯上什么
What would the boss focus on then
不会先盯上员工偶尔买一次的礼品
Not the occasional gifts employees buy
他会盯上所有人每天都要用的基础服务
He would focus on the basic services everyone uses every day
汉武帝做的事
What Emperor Wu did
就是把盐和铁收归国家控制
Was to bring salt and iron under state control
这就是历史上很有名的盐铁专营
This is the famous Salt and Iron Monopoly in history
盐负责日常消费
Salt handled daily consumption
铁负责生产工具和兵器
Iron handled production tools and weapons
一个管嘴巴
One controlled the mouth
一个管生产
One controlled production
这两个东西被控制住
With both of these under control
国家就有了稳定现金流
The state had a stable cash flow
后来到了前 81 年
Later in 81 BC
汉朝还专门开过一次大辩论
The Han Dynasty held a major debate
主题就是盐铁政策到底要不要继续
On whether the salt and iron policy should continue
这场辩论后来被整理成盐铁论
This debate was compiled into the Discourses on Salt and Iron
你可以把它理解成古代版的经济政策听证会
You can think of it as an ancient economic policy hearing
一边说
One side argued
国家不控制盐铁
Without state control of salt and iron
就没钱保边疆 平物价 管大局
There would be no money to defend borders stabilize prices and manage the big picture
另一边说
The other side argued
国家垄断太多民间商人没有活力
Too much state monopoly kills private sector vitality
老百姓负担太重
The burden on ordinary people is too heavy
你发现没有
Have you noticed
两千多年前的人
People from over two thousand years ago
已经在争今天还在争的问题
Were already debating the same issues we debate today
国家应该多管一点还是少管一点
Should the state control more or less
市场自由重要还是财政安全重要
Is market freedom more important or fiscal security
效率重要还是稳定重要
Is efficiency more important or stability
盐只是表面
Salt is just the surface
背后争的是一个国家怎么拿钱
Behind it is a debate about how a state takes money
又怎么花钱
And how it spends it
如果你是普通人
If you are an ordinary person
你可能会天然讨厌垄断
You might naturally hate monopolies
因为垄断意味着价格不完全由你决定
Because monopoly means prices are not fully up to you
但如果你是国家你会看到另一面
But if you are the state you see another side
边疆要守
Frontiers must be defended
灾荒要救
Disasters must be relieved
道路要修
Roads must be built
军队要养
Armies must be maintained
这些公共成本总要有人买单
Someone has to pay for all these public costs
问题只是
The question is only
这个单是明着交
Do you pay it openly
还是藏在盐价里交
Or is it hidden in the price of salt
盐铁专营最厉害的地方就在这里
This is where the Salt and Iron Monopoly was most brilliant
它把财政问题包装成了日常消费
It turned a fiscal problem into everyday consumption
你买一袋盐
You buy a bag of salt
国家多一笔收入
The state gets more revenue
你吃一顿饭
You eat a meal
帝国多一点续航
The empire gets more staying power
这听起来很夸张
This sounds exaggerated
但财政的本质
But the essence of fiscal policy
本来就不是一笔惊天动地的大钱
Is never about one earth shattering fortune
而是无数小钱
It is about countless small amounts
稳定地流向同一个地方
Steadily flowing to the same place
一个人一天只交一点
One person pays a little every day
一千万人每天都交一点
Ten million people pay a little every day
这就不是一点了
That is no longer a little
这叫规模
That is scale
这叫现金流
That is cash flow
这叫帝国的底气
That is the confidence of an empire
所以你看
So you see
盐不是因为神秘才重要
Salt is not important because it is mysterious
盐是因为普通才重要
Salt is important because it is ordinary
越普通越高频
The more ordinary the higher the frequency
越高频越稳定
The higher the frequency the more stable
越稳定越适合被制度化
The more stable the easier to institutionalize
这就是第二层秘密
This is the second secret
能撑起大系统的往往不是爆款
What sustains a big system is usually not a blockbuster
而是刚需
But a necessity
爆款让人兴奋
Blockbusters get people excited
刚需让系统活下去
Necessities keep systems alive
如果盐只是赚钱工具
If salt were just a money making tool
那故事还不够完整
The story would not be complete
真正有意思的是
What is really interesting
盐既能撑起帝国也能撬动帝国
Is that salt could both sustain and topple an empire
1930 年印度发生过一件很有名的事
In 1930 something famous happened in India
甘地带着追随者
Gandhi led his followers
从阿默达巴德附近出发
From near Ahmedabad
一路走到海边的丹地
All the way to the coast at Dandi
这就是盐进军
This was the Salt March
他们反抗的
What they were fighting against
不是一件听起来宏大的事
Was not something that sounds grand
不是王位
Not a throne
不是军队
Not an army
不是石油
Not oil
而是盐
But salt
当时英国殖民政府控制印度的盐生产和销售
At that time the British colonial government controlled Indias salt production and sales
印度人不能随便自己制盐
Indians could not freely make their own salt
一个靠海的国家普通人面对海水
A country surrounded by sea where ordinary people faced the ocean
却不能自由得到盐
Yet could not freely obtain salt
你想想这个画面
Imagine that scene
海就在眼前
The sea is right there
盐就在水里
The salt is in the water
但制度告诉你这不是你的
But the system tells you this is not yours
这个时候盐就不只是商品了
At this point salt was no longer just a commodity
它变成了一种羞辱感
It became a sense of humiliation
为什么甘地选盐
Why did Gandhi choose salt
因为盐太普通了
Because salt was so ordinary
普通到每个印度人都懂
Ordinary enough that every Indian understood
农民懂
Farmers understood
工人懂
Workers understood
老人懂
The elderly understood
孩子也懂
Even children understood
如果他讲复杂的宪政理论
If he had talked about complex constitutional theory
很多人听不懂
Many people would not have understood
如果他讲贸易 关税 殖民财政
If he had talked about trade tariffs colonial fiscal policy
普通人可能没感觉
Ordinary people might not have felt anything
但他讲盐
But when he talked about salt
所有人立刻明白
Everyone immediately understood
原来连我吃饭这件事
So even the act of eating
都被别人控制了
Was being controlled by someone else
这就是盐的第三层秘密
This is the third secret of salt
它不只是一种经济品
It is not just an economic good
它还是一种共识品
It is a consensus good
越普通的东西
The more ordinary something is
越容易让所有人形成共同感受
The easier it is for everyone to share a common feeling
你被一个高端奢侈品收割
If you get exploited by a luxury brand
别人可能没感觉
Others might not feel it
但你被米 盐 水 电 房租 通讯费收割
But if you get exploited by rice salt water electricity rent phone bills
所有人都会感到痛
Everyone feels the pain
因为这些东西不分阶层
Because these things do not discriminate by class
穷人要用
Poor people need them
富人也要用
Rich people need them too
只是穷人的痛感更强
It is just that poor people feel the pain more
所以盐能成为反抗的符号
So salt could become a symbol of resistance
不是因为它贵
Not because it was expensive
而是因为它把抽象的不公平
But because it turned abstract injustice
变成了每个人舌尖上的感觉
Into something everyone could taste
这里有一个很重要的认知
Here is an important insight
普通人反感的往往不是付钱
What ordinary people resent is usually not paying
而是没得选
It is having no choice
如果你觉得一件东西贵你可能会忍
If you think something is expensive you might endure it
但如果你发现自己根本没有选择权
But if you realize you have no choice at all
你会生气
You get angry
这也是今天很多商业模式翻车的原因
This is also why many business models crash today
会员自动续费
Auto renewing subscriptions
大数据杀熟
Algorithmic price discrimination
平台抽成越来越高
Platforms taking bigger and bigger cuts
外卖商家被平台绑住
Takeout merchants tied to platforms
创作者被流量规则绑住
Creators tied to traffic rules
用户一边用一边骂
Users complain while still using them
为什么
Why
不是因为大家不愿意付费
Not because people do not want to pay
而是因为入口被控制以后
But because once the gateway is controlled
选择权越来越少
Choice keeps shrinking
当一个系统既离不开又说不清
When a system is indispensable opaque
还绕不过
And impossible to bypass
它就会从便利变成压迫
It goes from being convenient to being oppressive
盐的故事提醒我们
The story of salt reminds us
任何入口生意都有一条危险边界
Any gateway business has a dangerous boundary
它可以收费
It can charge
但不能让人觉得自己被关起来
But it cannot make people feel locked up
它可以赚钱
It can make money
但不能让人觉得自己没有退路
But it cannot make people feel trapped
真正高级的商业不是把人锁死
Truly great business is not about locking people in
而是让人明知道可以走却愿意留下
It is about making people willing to stay even when they know they can leave
讲到这里你可能会问
At this point you might ask
盐的故事跟我今天有什么关系
What does the story of salt have to do with me today
关系很大
A lot
因为每个时代都有自己的盐
Because every era has its own salt
古代的盐是身体离不开的刚需
In ancient times salt was a necessity the body could not do without
工业时代的电是机器离不开的刚需
In the industrial age electricity was a necessity machines could not do without
互联网时代的流量
In the internet age traffic
是生意离不开的刚需
Was a necessity businesses could not do without
AI 时代的新盐
The new salt in the AI era
可能是算力 模型 数据 接口
Might be computing power models data APIs
也可能是你每天用来提问和做决策的那个入口
Or it might be that gateway you use every day to ask questions and make decisions
你今天问 AI 写方案
Today you ask AI to write proposals
明天让 AI 做表格
Tomorrow you let AI make spreadsheets
后天让 AI 帮你判断要不要买一个东西
The day after you let AI help you decide whether to buy something
慢慢地你会发现
Gradually you will find
它不再只是工具
It is no longer just a tool
它开始变成你的思考入口
It starts becoming your gateway for thinking
当一个工具变成入口
When a tool becomes a gateway
它的商业逻辑就变了
Its business logic changes
早期它会很便宜
Early on it will be very cheap
甚至免费
Even free
因为它要培养你的习惯
Because it needs to build your habits
等你离不开它它才有真正的定价权
Only when you cannot leave it does it gain real pricing power
这和盐很像
This is a lot like salt
一开始你觉得只是加一点味道
At first you think it just adds a little flavor
后来你发现每顿饭都少不了它
Later you realize you cannot have a meal without it
AI 产品也是这样
AI products are the same
今天你觉得只是帮你省时间
Today you think it just saves you time
以后它可能会影响你怎么学习 怎么工作 怎么做决定
Later it might affect how you learn work and make decisions
所以普通人真正要学的
So what ordinary people really need to learn
不是每天追哪个模型更强
Is not which model is stronger every day
而是学会识别
But to learn to recognize
谁在掌握新的入口
Who is controlling the new gateway
谁在掌握新的盐
Who is controlling the new salt
你可以问自己三个问题
You can ask yourself three questions
第一这个东西是不是高频
First is this thing high frequency
我是不是每天都用
Do I use it every day
第二这个东西是不是刚需
Second is this thing essential
不用它我的效率是不是明显下降
Without it does my efficiency obviously drop
第三这个东西是不是低替代
Third is this thing hard to substitute
我换掉它的成本是不是越来越高
Is the cost of switching higher and higher
只要三个答案都是是
If all three answers are yes
你就要警惕
You should be alert
它正在从工具变成基础设施
It is going from being a tool to being infrastructure
对普通人来说
For ordinary people
最好的策略不是拒绝它
The best strategy is not to reject it
拒绝盐的人最后吃饭没味道
People who rejected salt ended up with tasteless food
拒绝 AI 的人未来工作会很吃力
People who reject AI will struggle to work in the future
但你也不能完全依赖它
But you cannot depend on it entirely either
完全依赖一个入口
Depending entirely on one gateway
就等于把自己的选择权交出去
Means handing over your power of choice
你可以用它
You can use it
但要保留迁移能力
But keep the ability to migrate
你可以订阅它
You can subscribe to it
但要知道替代方案
But know the alternatives
你可以让 AI 帮你写
You can let AI help you write
但不能让 AI 替你判断
But you cannot let AI judge for you
因为真正值钱的从来不是盐本身
Because what is truly valuable is never the salt itself
而是谁掌握了盐从哪里来卖给谁
But who controls where the salt comes from and who it is sold to
按什么规则卖
And under what rules
回到开头那袋盐
Back to that bag of salt from the beginning
它便宜
It is cheap
安静
Quiet
不起眼
Unremarkable
但它让我们看见一个很残酷的真相
But it reveals a brutal truth
世界上最强的控制
The strongest control in the world
往往不是控制你一年买一次的东西
Is usually not controlling what you buy once a year
而是控制你每天都离不开的东西
But controlling what you cannot live without every day
所以下次你在厨房里撒盐的时候
So next time you sprinkle salt in your kitchen
可以想一想
You might want to think
这袋几块钱的盐曾经让帝国续命
This bag of salt costing a few yuan once kept empires alive
也曾经让普通人反抗
And once made ordinary people rise up
它提醒你的不是怎么炒菜
It does not remind you how to cook
而是怎么识别这个世界真正的入口
But how to recognize the real gateways of this world
谁控制入口谁就控制价格
Whoever controls the gateway controls the price
谁控制刚需谁就控制选择
Whoever controls the necessity controls the choice
谁能看懂盐
Whoever can read salt
谁就能看懂一个时代的财富流向
Can read the flow of wealth in an era